people mention intervals all the time
when talking about music theory but what
are intervals in music they're really
just the names or the labels we give to
different sized gaps between any two
notes and you need to know them first
because we then use those names as like
an alphabet to describe how to do things
like build chords and scales or pick out
which notes we've used in a melody for
example so this is a theory thing but I
like to think of it as a really useful
one practical kind of theory because
once you start integrating it into your
playing it really helps you find things
and memorize things on the piano so much
easier learn more and understand what it
is that you're playing recognize what it
is that you hear or recreate the sounds
or musical effects that you've learned
basically just speak the language of
music more fluently which in the long
run makes you a better musician in this
video I'm going to tell you everything
you need to know about them to get
started and how to name everyone this
channels your guide for developing all
the different skills and knowledge you
need to become a better piano player and
musician so if that's something you want
to do consider clicking the subscribe
button and the notification bell so you
don't miss out on anything you need to
learn each different sized interval has
a unique character or flavor of sound as
I like to think of it and with music
it's really about the relationship
between notes and the way that they
interact that creates these different
emotional qualities more than just what
the notes are themselves and that's a
really fundamental part of how music
works here's why me if we start at C for
example between here and the next C and
octave the notes are divided up equally
giving us 12 different intervals
remember there's nothing different about
the Black Keys they're just the buttons
for the notes so starting from seeing
all these other notes are a different
distance away from the starting point
and we can measure how big the gap is by
Counting half steps which just means
moving up to a note right next door so
from the C this note is one half-step
away two half steps three four five
remember there's no black note here so
this is also a half
that six seven eight nine ten eleven
twelve so you can just count and
describe things that way but that's not
always the most useful system so we use
a number system for the interval names
those names are something you really
need to know but there's a couple of
other concepts too first so I'll come
back to that in a minute I do have a
worksheet available to linked in the
description with a clear list of all the
intervals you need for reference and a
reminder of everything you're learning
in this video each of these different
sized gaps or intervals has a different
relationship and sounds unique we can
think of intervals two ways harmonic
playing them together on melodic playing
them apart and then you can go up or
down we've been starting from C but an
important thing to understand is this
works no matter which know you start on
or as we say in different keys so here
to here is a half-step here to here is
also a half-step so it's here so even
though those intervals use different
notes and they look like different
shapes and they didn't sound identical
because there are different pitches they
are still the same size and they have
the same quality so I could recreate the
same melody using them so that one
happens to be used for the jaws thing
this is the same for any sized interval
this one here which is five five steps
one two three four five can be used to
play here comes the bride and it's going
to sound like that wherever I do it so
from D five half steps one two three
four five from b-flat five half steps
one two three four five they all look
different but they all sound like here
comes the bride just lower and higher
versions the intervals all sound
different and they're like a list of
ingredients that we can use different
combinations of those ingredients can
create different chords and scales and
we play with them to make music quick
example from C again from here if we
have all these intervals up to the next
C to choose from this combination is
called a C major chord this combination
is called a C minor chord
these ones become a c-major scale these
ones become C minor scale so all they
really are is certain selections of
intervals and when you know the names
you can describe any chord or scale in
the same way like a chef needs to know
what their ingredients taste like which
common dishes use which ingredients and
what goes well with what as musicians we
need to do the same with intervals you
have to learn to find them confidently
on the keyboard because the shapes all
look different in different keys read
them if you're a reader and also really
importantly learn to recognize them by
ear
now they're all large topics for another
time but before you do any of those you
need to know how to label them these are
all the basic labels you need to know
and learn there are other more advanced
labels you may come across in the future
but learning those straightaway would
only complicate things for no real good
reason along the way if you can think of
any melodies that sound like they start
with any of these intervals then let me
know in the comments so back to see us
it's always the clearest one to work
from first if we just ignore the Black
Keys for a moment we can number the
notes by how many letters away they are
so it seems to start we call it number
one C 2 D is 2 or a second because it
uses two letters e is then a third
because it uses three letters F would be
a fourth fifth sixth seventh and then
back at C would be an eighth or octave
so let's bring the black notes back in
because C was one and D was a second
that leaves out this note here so in
music we actually have two versions of a
second minor and major so when we start
from C D flat would be called a minor
second and then that D would be the
major second we tend to use a lowercase
M for minor and an uppercase M for major
this is the same for thirds so we just
got to that D so the next note e flat
would be called a minor third and E
would be a major third then we get to
four and five now four and five are
called perfect fourth and
perfect fifth the name kind of implies
that they're the most consonant and
stable sounding intervals we don't have
a major and a minor version of four and
five so this note in between them is the
one where you need to know a few
different names because the alternate
names are used quite a lot so if we were
naming that note we would call it an
f-sharp or a G flat but if F is four in
this case and G is five we can also call
it a sharp four because it's sharp above
the fourth note sharp means a half-step
up or a flat five because it's flat
below the fifth note flat means a half
step down so they get cooled that a lot
but they're sort of proper interval
names are Augmented fourth and that sort
of means the same thing as sharp you
raise it by a half step so Augmented
fourth because it's come up from the
fourth note or diminished fifth because
it's come down like flat from the fifth
note so Augmented fourth and diminished
fifth this one also gets called a
tritone a lot of the time tone means the
same thing as a whole step we say tone
in the UK and it's three tones away one
two three it's also sometimes nicknamed
The Devil's interval so then six and
seven so just like two and three these
two would be major six and seven and
then the two notes below them would be
minor six and seven sometimes we say
flat six and flat seven two then eight
or perfect eighth but normally it just
gets called an octave so numbers two
three six and seven can be major or
minor minor is always the smaller size
the one closer to the note that you
started from and these tend to be the
more colorful notes you use minor being
the darker one and major usually the
brighter sounding one four five and
eight are perfect and the one in between
four and five has those few different
names you need to learn I wouldn't worry
about when to use which name right at
the moment though so this order is true
no matter where you start so I'm going
to do an example from a if a is now one
then we'd have - second major second
minor third major third
4 sharp 4 5 - 6 major 6 - 7 major 7
octave so these are the names of the
intervals and you can start practicing
them by just reciting them in order and
maybe following along in half steps on
the keyboard at the same time but to
really get them fluent you need to start
finding them on the piano in different
keys training your ears to hear them and
paying attention to which ones you're
using on different kinds of chords and
scales and playing music I'm going to do
more videos on those kind of things at
some point and I'll pin them in the
comments when I do or - make sure you
don't miss out on that or any other
content it's going to help you develop
your piano playing you can click
subscribe and the notification bar so
YouTube actually tells you when there's
a new video up don't forget there's a
link to that worksheet in the
description with everything I've talked
about here all the names plus some of
the alternate names that you may come
across in the future for reference let
me know in the comments and give the
video a like if you found it helpful as
that really helps out the channel to see
how some of these intervals are actually
used to build major and minor chords you
can click here or for a really useful
trick to help you memorize and visualize
all your major scales click here thanks
for watching
[Music]